<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>HIStory : An electronic transcription</title>
            <!-- In the final project, I would like to anonymise the author of the letters with consideration to ethics. With Mats I discussed the possibility to slightly blurr the name in the facsimile. I would like to have a diplomatic witness, but when the name comes up, I would like to show that I obliterate the info. How could I do that? -->
            <principal>
               <forename>Maud</forename>
               <surname>Guichard-Marneur</surname>
            </principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selected, transcribed and Encoded by </resp>
               <persName>
                  <forename>Maud</forename>
                  <surname>Guichard-Marneur</surname>
               </persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>
               <forename>Maud</forename>
               <surname>Guichard-Marneur</surname></authority>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <street>Gamla Björlandavägen 164</street>
                  <settlement>Göteborg</settlement>
                  <postCode>41728</postCode>
                  <country>Sweden</country>
               </address>
               <affiliation>University of Borås, Sweden</affiliation>
               <date when="2022-05-05">5 May 2022</date>
            </pubPlace>
            <availability>
               <p>These files are made available for public interest, including scientific and
                  historical research, in accordance with GDPR Chap.9, art.89 on safeguards and
                  derogations for archiving purposes. The high-resolution files may only be
                  communicated by contacting the responsible authority of the present digital
                  transcription. </p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>The present transcription is undertaken as part of a potentially wider digitizing
               project initiated as part of the course on digitizing cultural heritage, Master in
               library and information science, digital libraries and information services, at the
               University of Borås. </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Personal letters, printed material and course notes from a rescued
                     personnal archive in possession of the instigator of the present digital
                     transcription </repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc material="paper">
                        <extent> Three hand-written letters <dimensions scope="all" type="leaf"
                              unit="cm">
                              <height>21</height>
                              <width>14,7</width>
                           </dimensions> one hand written letter <dimensions scope="all" type="leaf"
                              unit="cm">
                              <height>29,7</height>
                              <width>21</width>
                           </dimensions>and one printed letter <dimensions scope="all" type="leaf"
                              unit="cm">
                              <height>29,7</height>
                              <width>21</width>
                           </dimensions></extent>

                        <collation>Great care has been given to preserve the order in which
                           documents were bundled together, often in folders with titles. The draft
                           letters written in pencil as well as the printed letter to Maréchal
                           Pétain on the occasion of his birthday were grouped together and are all
                           from the same time period (1941) when the priest was prisoner of war in
                           Germany during WWII. </collation>
                        <condition>
                           <p> The selected items in the archive are in relative good condition
                              considering the poor storage condition they have been in. Two letters
                              certainly come from the same notebook with ruled papper. Each sheet
                              was detached from it. The paper sheets are intact but yellowed with
                              time and slighly stained. One A4 letter has been preserved folded and
                              is nearly split at the folding crease rendering one written line
                              barely legible.</p>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This is a sample of a potentially larger digitizing project that aims at creating a
               research portal where personal archives become the main point of entry for a more
               human-centred history where individual trajectories intersect with political and
               historical events as well as institutions. The project starting point is the display
               of archive material that belonged to one individual, a French priest who was educated
               in the 30s in France, became a war prisoner during WWII and later an advocate for
               freedom of (religious) education. There are many points of (research) interest that
               are raised through one personal archive. Indeed, each archival item acquires its full
               meaning in the context of its own archive. In the case of the French priest archive,
               it is absolutely fascinating to look at the seminar notes and course booklets to
               deepen our understanding of religious, Catholic, education in France in the 1930s.
               Likewise, the material saved over time by one priest reveals an intersting trajectory
               when thinking about the Church position during WWII with regard to Nazi Germany and
               Vichy France. In the case of the priest's personal archive, it is interesting to note
               that Vichy France aligned publications from the early years of WWII had been
               preserved by the priest. Towards, the end of the war and soon after the war, another
               type of material had been considered worthy of keeping. For example, the archive
               contains a German newspaper published in May 1945 that showed in its front page
               striking photos of victims and survisvors at concentration camps. These choices are
               in themselves meaningful. The personal archive also holds a rare catalogue of the
               exhibition "Hitlerian crimes" that was held at the Grand Palais in Paris in the
               summer 1945. Hence the individual documents, as well as the personal archive as a
               whole offer great research potential about the following themes, but not exclusively:
               Religious catholic education, war prisonners, WWII, the Church establishment, history
               of mentality and Vichy France. </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>The whole archive in my possession is indeed only a sample of the priest's archive.
               The archive material that I rescued in 2003 from what was sent for garbage collection
               outside the Clarisse Convent, rue de Briseux, in Rennes, is only a sample collected
               at random. Indeed there were many more boxes, many of them had been already
               contaminated by dog urine. I rescued what seemed the most interesting in a few minute
               timeframe. What had originally attacted my eye was the Vichy France publications and
               the seminar notes from the 1930s. Soon after I started going through the few boxes I
               had collected with the aim of indexing the material, but lack of time stopped me in
               my endeavour. In 2022, I finally got an opportunity to get back to this archive that
               had been stored in France. A pre-selection was brought to Sweden where I started to
               read and research the documents. For the digitization project I sampled and digitised
               a few, considered most interesting and/or striking documents from three different
               periods of the priest's life: the 1930s, WWII and post WWII. However, for online
               presentation I focused on marking up selected WWII letters that I present here</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <normalization>
               <p>The abbreviation for 'numéro' includes an 'o' in superscript that has not been
                  rendered in the transcription. </p>
            </normalization>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>The hyphenation has been faithfully transcribed and the line breaks rendered in
                  the transcription</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <quotation>
               <p> References to text from newspaper articles have been transcribed as TEI quote
                  with a rendition 'quote' </p>
            </quotation>
            <segmentation>
               <p>The transcription is organised to correspond to the way the text is divided on
                  each page of each facsimile.</p>
            </segmentation>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>

         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="JJ">Written by Joseph Jouzel</handNote>
         </handNotes>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fr">French</language>
            <language ident="de">German</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="personJJ">
                  <persName>
                     <forename>Joseph</forename>
                     <surname>Jouzel</surname>
                  </persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="personCommandant">
                  <name>Commandant de l'Offlag XIII A</name>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="personScapini">
                  <name><ref target="https://francearchives.fr/fr/authorityrecord/FRAN_NP_051226"
                        >Scapini</ref></name>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            <listOrg>
               <org xml:id="TU">
                  <orgName xml:lang="fr"><ref target="https://data.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cb32879084h"
                        >Trait d'Union</ref></orgName>

               </org>
               <org xml:id="PS">
                  <orgName xml:lang="fr"><ref target="https://data.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/cb34519208g"
                        >Paris-Soir</ref></orgName>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="FS">
                  <orgName xml:lang="de"><ref
                        target="https://fr.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Frontstalag&amp;oldid=187127738"
                        >Frontstsalag</ref></orgName>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="AK">
                  <orgName xml:lang="de">Arbeitskommando</orgName>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="ST">
                  <orgName xml:lang="de"><ref
                        target="https://www.americanairmuseum.com/place/226952">Stalag XIII
                     B</ref></orgName>
               </org>
               <org xml:id="OF">
                  <orgName xml:lang="de"><ref
                        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Oflag_XIII-A&amp;oldid=1079979451"
                     /></orgName>
               </org>
            </listOrg>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8374">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated March 20 1941 (recto)</label>
            <figDesc> Recto of a draft letter, dated 20 March 1941, in which the priest reports on
               his different assignments and locations since he was made prisoner of war on 17 June
               1940. The letter to the Kommandatur aims to request payment for his work as
               nurse.</figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8374_object" url="DSCF8374.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8374crop_full" url="DSCF8374crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8374crop_thumb" url="DSCF8374crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8375">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated March 20 1941 (verso)</label>
            <figDesc> Verso of a draft letter, dated 20 March 1941, in which the priest reports on
               his different assignments and locations since he was made prisoner of war on 17 June
               1940. The letter to the Kommandatur aims to request payment for his work as
               nurse.</figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8375_object" url="DSCF8375.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8375crop_full" url="DSCF8375crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8375crop_thumb" url="DSCF8375crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8370-1">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated 30 April 1941 with an excerpt from the newspaper Trait d'Union
               (Recto)</label>
            <figDesc>Recto of a draft letter, citing an excerpt from the newspaper Trait d'Union,
               adressed to the Kommandatur and seeking release from the war prisoner camp. </figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8370-1_object" url="DSCF8310-1.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8370-1crop_full" url="DSCF8370-1crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8370-1crop_thumb" url="DSCF8370-1crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8371">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated 30 April 1941 with an excerpt from the newspaper Trait d'Union
               (Verso)</label>
            <figDesc>Verso of a draft letter, citing an excerpt from the newspaper Trait d'Union,
               adressed to the Kommandatur and seeking release from the war prisoner camp. </figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8371_object" url="DSCF8371.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8371crop_full" url="DSCF8371crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8371crop_thumb" url="DSCF8371crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8366-1">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated 30 April 1941 referring to an excerpt of Paris-Soir
               (Recto)</label>
            <figDesc> Recto of a draft letter,dated 30 April 1941, citing an excerpt from the
               newspaper Paris-Soir, addressed to the Kommandatur and seeking release from the war
               prisoner camp. </figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8366-1_object" url="DSCF8366-1.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8366-1crop_full" url="DSCF8366-1crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8366-1crop_thumb" url="DSCF8366-1crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8367">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated 30 April 1941 referring to an excerpt of Paris-Soir
               (Verso)</label>
            <figDesc>Verso of a draft letter, dated 30 April 1941, citing an excerpt from the
               newspaper Paris-Soir, addressed to the Kommandatur and seeking release from the war
               prisoner camp. </figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8367_object" url="DSCF8367.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8367crop_full" url="DSCF8367crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8367crop_thumb" url="DSCF8367crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8383">
         <figure>
            <label>Draft letter dated 30 April 1941 referring to an excerpt of Trait d'Union in the
               body of the letter (Recto)</label>
            <figDesc> Recto of a draft letter, dated 30 April 1941, citing in the body of the letter
               an excerpt from the newspaper Trait d'Union, addressed to the Kommandatur and seeking
               release from the war prisoner camp.</figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8383_object" url="DSCF8383.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8383crop_full" url="DSCF8383crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8383crop_thumb" url="DSCF8383crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8384">
         <figure>
            <label> Draft letter dated 30 April 1941 referring to an excerpt of Trait d'Union in the
               body of the letter (Verso)</label>
            <figDesc> Verso of a draft letter, dated 30 April 1941, citing in the body of the letter
               an excerpt of the newspaper Trait d'Union, addressed to the Kommandatur and seeking
               release from the war prisoner camp.</figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8384_object" url="DSCF8384.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8384crop_full" url="DSCF8384crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8384crop_thumb" url="DSCF8384crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8350">
         <figure>
            <label> Printed letter to wish Maréchal Pétain a happy birthday (recto)</label>
            <figDesc> Recto of a printed letter, addressed to Maréchal Pétain on his birthday, from
               the war prisoners of the Oflag XIII A. Unsigned copy. </figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8350_object" url="DSCF8350.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8350crop_full" url="DSCF8350crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8350crop_thumb" url="DSCF8350_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="DSCF8351">
         <figure>
            <label>Printed letter to wish Maréchal Pétain a happy birthday (verso)</label>
            <figDesc> Verso of a printed letter, addressed to Maréchal pétain on his birthday, from
               the war prisoners of the Oflag XIII A. Unsigned copy.</figDesc>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8351_object" url="DSCF8351.tiff"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8351crop_full" url="DSCF8351crop.png"/>
            <graphic xml:id="DSCF8351crop_thumb" url="DSCF8351crop_thumb.jpeg"/>
         </figure>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="prose" hand="#JJ">
            <pb facs="#DSCF8374"/>
            <!-- In this letter, the year seems to have retrospectively been added to dates/time periods. The year is written in pencil but in bold.
               As confirmation that the year dates were added after the fact is that although the letter is dated 1941-03-20, a date (rendered in bold) indicates 'until 1941-07-27.'
            I have rendered this editorial change with the add element-->
            <opener>
               <date when="1941-03-20" rend="right">Le 20 mars 1941</date>
               <persName ref="#JJ" rend="left"> Le <w>caporal </w>
                  <w>infirmier</w>
                  <surname rend="allcaps" style="big">Jouzel</surname>
                  <forename rend="allcaps" style="small">Joseph,</forename>
               </persName><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="indent">numéro<num corresp="#personJJ">4526</num>, Block <num
                     type="ordinal" value="3">III</num>.</affiliation><lb/>
               <salute rend="indent">A monsieur le <w xml:lang="fr">Commandant</w> de l'<placeName
                     xml:lang="de">Oflag <lb/>
                     <num type="ordinal" value="13">XIII</num> A. Unterlager A.</placeName></salute>
            </opener>
            <p><add place="margin">Objet: Perception de la <w>solde</w>
               d'<w>infirmier</w>.</add></p>
            <p rend="indent">J’ai l’honneur de solliciter de<lb/> votre bienveillance de vouloir
               bien payer<lb/> ma solde d’infirmier.</p>
            <p rend="indent">En effet, bien que reconnu comme<lb/> Sanitaire par les <w>Autorités
                  Militaires</w><lb/> Allemandes, je certifie n’avoir encore<lb/> perçu <emph
                  rend="underlined">aucune solde d’aucune sorte</emph> depuis<lb/> que je suis
               prisonnier, alors que des<lb/>
               <w>Sanitaires</w>, dans le même cas que le mien,<lb/> perçoivent <num value="1"
                  >un</num><measure type="currency"><w>mark</w></measure> par jour.</p>
            <p>Voici à titre documentaire, mes dif<lb/>férentes <w>affectations</w>, depuis le <date
                  when="1940-06-17">17 juin 1940</date><lb/> ,date à laquelle j’ai été fait
               prison-<lb/>nier à <placeName>Vitteaux (Côte-d’Or)</placeName>: </p>
            <p>Affecté à l’<w>Hôpital</w> d'<placeName>
                  <settlement>Avallon</settlement>
                  <region>(Yonne)</region></placeName>, comme <w>infirmier</w> à la <w>salle
                  d’opérations</w>, du<lb/>
               <date when="--06-17">17 juin</date> au<date when="--07-19">19 juillet</date><add
                  rend="bold"><date>1940</date></add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <w>Interné</w> au camp de
                     <placeName><settlement>Cravant</settlement><region>(Yonne)</region></placeName>,
               du <date when="--07-19">19 juillet</date> au <date when="--10-22">22
                  octobre</date><add rend="bold"><date>1940</date></add>
            </p>
            <p>
               <w>Interné</w> au camp de
                     <placeName><settlement>Saint-Florentin</settlement><region>(Yonne)</region></placeName>,
                  <orgName ref="#FS"><w>Frontstalag</w>
                  <num type="cardinal">150</num></orgName>, du <date when="--10-22">22
                  octobre</date> au <date when="--10-29">29 octobre</date><add rend="bold"><date
                     when="1940">1940</date></add>
            </p>
            <p>Dirigé sur l’<placeName><country>Allemagne</country></placeName>le <date
                  when="--10-29">29 octobre</date> :</p>
            <p>A <placeName><settlement xml:lang="de">Grafenwöhr</settlement></placeName>, du <date
                  from="--11-01" to="--11-07"><num type="ordinal"><abbr>1er</abbr></num> au 7
                  novembre</date><add rend="bold"><date when="1940">1940</date></add></p>
            <p>A <placeName><settlement>Eger</settlement></placeName>
               <orgName type="acronym" ref="#AK"><w>(A.K. 34-31)</w></orgName>, du <date>7</date> au
                  <date when="--11-27">27 novembre</date></p>
            <p>A <placeName><settlement>Weiden</settlement></placeName>
               <orgName ref="#ST"><w>(Stalag XIII B)</w></orgName>, du <date when="--11-27">27
                  novembre</date> au <date when="1941-01-11">11 janvier 194 <emph style="bold"
                     >1</emph></date></p>
            <p>A <placeName><settlement>Nüruberg</settlement></placeName>
               <orgName ref="#OF"><w>(Oflag XIII A, Unterlager A)</w></orgName>, à partir du <date
                  when="1941-01-11">11 Janvier <del rend="overstrike">1941</del></date>. <add
                  rend="bold"> jusqu'au <date when="1941-07-23">23 juillet 1941.</date></add></p>
         </div>
         <div type="prose" hand="#JJ">
            <pb facs="#DSCF8370"/>
            <opener>
               <persName ref="#JJ" rend="left"><w>Caporal</w>
                  <w>infirmier</w>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname>Jouzel</surname>
               </persName><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="left"><abbr>No</abbr>:<num corresp="#personJJ"
                  >4526</num></affiliation><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="left">Block III</affiliation><lb/>
               <date when="1941-04-30" rend="right">Le 30 avril 1941</date>
               <salute>A monsieur le <w xml:lang="fr">Commandant</w> de l'<placeName xml:lang="de"
                     >Oflag <num type="ordinal" value="13">XIII</num> A</placeName></salute>
               <add place="margin" style="transform:rotate(-45deg)" rend="underlined">Non
                  expédié</add>
            </opener>

            <p>J’ai l’honneur de solliciter de votre <lb/>bienveillance de bien vouloir me rendre
               mon <w>livret <lb/>individuel</w> que je vous ai remis le 26 mars, à la <lb/>suite
               d’une réclamation concernant ma solde <lb/>d’<w>infirmier</w> – réclamation restée
               d’ailleurs <lb/>sans réponse. Ce livret contient ne effet toutes <lb/>les pièces
               prouvant ma qualité de <w>sanitaire</w>
               <lb/>et je ne peux m’en <sic>désaisir</sic>.</p>

            <p>A ce propos, je me permets de vous rap- <lb/>peler que vous avez déjà eu ce
                  <w>livret</w> en votre <lb/> possession, du 10 au 22 février, date <lb/>à laquelle
               la <w xml:lang="de">kommandantur</w> m’avait recon- <lb/>nu comme sanitaire. <pb
                  facs="#DSCF8371"/> De plus, le 24 fé- <lb/>vrier, le médecin militaire allemand,
               que j’a- <lb/>vais vu à l’infirmerie, m’avait également <lb/>inscrit comme
               sanitaire.</p>

            <p>D’autre part, le <title resp="#TU" rend="quote">Trait d’Union</title> du <lb/>24
               avril publie le texte de l’accord interve- <lb/>nu entre les autorités militaires
               allemandes <lb/>et m. l’Ambassadeur <persName>Scapini</persName>: <add place="above"
                  >Au 6e paragraphe il est dit</add><q resp="#TU" rend="quote"> Afin de <lb/>
                  compléter l’assistance sanitaire des prison- <lb/>niers de guerre, il est fait
                  appel aux mem-<lb/> bres du service sanitaire de l’armée <lb/>française. Le
                  personnel sanitaire qui ne <lb/>sera pas utilisé à cet effet sera bientôt
                  <lb/>libéré et renvoyé en France.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Or, depuis mon arrivée en Allemagne, <lb/> le <date when="1940-11-01">1er novembre
                  1940</date>, je n’ai jamais été <lb/>employé en tant que sanitaire : par
               <lb/>conséquent, ce paragraphe me concerne <lb/>particulièrement. C’est d’ailleurs,
               en vertu <lb/>de cet accord, que des infirmiers de mon <lb/>groupe sanitaire
               divisionnaire ont été <lb/>libérés dans le courant du mois de février. <lb/></p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Je vous serais donc très reconnaissant <lb/>de bien vouloir prendre en
                  considération <lb/>ma situation présente.</salute><lb/>
               <signed corresp="#personJJ" rend="right">J jouzel</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prose" hand="#JJ">
            <pb facs="#DSCF8366-1"/>
            <opener>
               <persName ref="#JJ" rend="left"><w>Caporal</w>
                  <w>infirmier</w>
                  <surname style="allcaps" rend="first">Jouzel</surname>
                  <!-- I have encountered 2 issues: JOUZEL is in all caps but I have tried rend:allcaps and style: allcaps without any success. Why? The other issue is thta in that letter the author writes his surnmae first. However even If I wrore the surname first it comes automatically second when I check the XHTML file. Why? How could I override this?  -->
                  <forename rend="second">Joseph</forename>
               </persName><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="left">
                  <abbr>no</abbr>
                  <w>matricule</w>
                  <num corresp="#personJJ">4526</num> 4526</affiliation><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="left">Block III</affiliation><lb/>
               <date when="1941-04-30" rend="right">Le 30 avril 1941</date><lb/>
               <salute>A monsieur le <w xml:lang="fr">Commandant</w> de l'<placeName xml:lang="de"
                     >Oflag <num type="ordinal" value="13">XIII</num> A</placeName>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p><add place="margin">Objet: Réclamation de <w>livret individuel</w>.</add> J’ai
               l’honneur de rappeler à <lb/> votre bienveillante attention que mon <w>livret
                  indi-<lb/>viduel</w> vous a été remis le 26 mars, à la suite<lb/> d’une
               réclamation concernant ma solde d’<w>in-<lb/>firmier</w>. Si cela est possible, je
               serais dési-<lb/>reux de rentrer en sa possession, car il con-<lb/>tient toutes les
               pièces prouvant ma qualité<lb/> de <w>Sanitaire</w>.</p>
            <p>A ce propos, je me permets de vous<lb/> rappeler que vous avez déjà eu ce livret<lb/>
               en votre possession, du 20 au 22 février,<lb/> date à laquelle la <w xml:lang="de"
                  >Kommandantur</w> m’a-<lb/>vait reconnu comme <w>Sanitaire</w>. De plus<lb/> le 24
               février, le médecin militaire alle-<lb/>mand, que j’avais vu à l’infirmerie,<lb/>
               m’avait également inscrit comme<lb/>
               <w>Sanitaire</w>.</p>
            <pb facs="#DSCF8367"/>
            <p>C’est pourquoi, j’exprime à nouveau<lb/> mon respectueux étonnement de n’avoir
               pas<lb/> encore été payé comme <w>infirmier</w>, alors<lb/> que les autres
               Sanitaires, qui se trouvent<lb/> dans mon cas, perçoivent depuis longtemps<lb/> un
               mark par jour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed corresp="#personJJ" rend="right">J Jouzel</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Extrait de <title resp="#PS" rend="quote">Paris-Soir</title>, du <date
                     when="1941-04-26">26/4/41</date>,</p>
               <lb/>
               <p rend="underlined"><placeName>Berlin</placeName>, <date when="1941-04-20">20
                     avril</date></p>
               <lb/>
               <q rend="quote">Les autorités militaires ont décidé que<lb/> les <w>Prêtres</w>
                  français prisonniers en Allemagne, ne seront<lb/> plus employés qu’à
                     l’<w>assistance religieuse</w> de leurs ca-<lb/>marades. Ils pourront
                  également, s’ils y consentent,<lb/> être utilisés comme interprètes. Ils ne seront
                  sou-<lb/>mis au travail manuel que s’ils en expriment le<lb/> désir.</q>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="prose" hand="#JJ">
            <pb facs="#DSCF8383"/>
            <opener>
               <date when="1941-04-30" rend="right">Le 30 avril 1941</date><lb/>
               <persName ref="#JJ" rend="left"><w>Caporal</w>
                  <w>infirmier</w>
                  <surname rend="allcaps" style="big">Jouzel</surname>
                  <forename rend="allcaps" style="small">Joseph</forename>
               </persName><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="left"><abbr>No</abbr>:<num corresp="#personJJ"
                  >4526</num></affiliation><lb/>
               <affiliation rend="left">Block III</affiliation><lb/>
               <salute>A monsieur le <w xml:lang="fr">Commandant</w> de l'<placeName xml:lang="de"
                     >Oflag <num type="ordinal" value="13">XIII</num> A</placeName></salute>
               <lb/>
            </opener>
            <p rend="indent"> J’ai l’honneur de solliciter de votre<lb/> bienveillance de bien
               vouloir me rendre mon livret<lb/> individuel que je vous ai remis le 26 mars, à
               la<lb/> suite d’une réclamation concernant ma solde<lb/> d’infirmier – réclamation
               restée d’ailleurs sans<lb/> réponse. Ce livret contient en effet toutes les<lb/>
               pièces prouvant ma qualité de sanitaire et je<lb/> ne peux m’en
               <sic>désaisir</sic>.</p>
            <p rend="indent"> A ce propos, je me permets de vous<lb/> rappeler que vous avez déjà eu
               ce livret en votre<lb/> possession, du 10 au 22 février, date à laquelle<lb/> la
               Kommandatur m’avait reconnu comme<lb/> sanitaire. De plus, le 24 février, le
               médecin<lb/> militaire allemand, que j’avais vu à l’infirme-<lb/>rie, m’avait
               également inscrit comme sanitaire.</p>
            <p rend="indent">D’autre part, le <title resp="#TU" rend="quote">Trait
               d’Union</title><lb/> du <date when="--04-24">24 avril</date> publie le texte de
               l’accord<lb/> intervenu entre les autorités militaires alle-<lb/>mandes et m.
               l’Ambassadeur Scapini. Au<pb facs="#DSCF8384"/> paragraphe sixième il est dit : <q
                  resp="#TU" rend="quote">« Afin de<lb/> compléter l’assistance sanitaire des
                  prisonniers<lb/> de guerre, il est fait appel aux membres du<lb/> Service
                  sanitaire de l’armée française. Le <lb/>personnel sanitaire qui ne sera pas
                  utilisé à<lb/> cet effet sera bientôt libéré et renvoyé en France. »</q></p>
            <p rend="indent">Or depuis mon arrivée en -<lb/>, le <date when="1940-11-01">1er
                  novembre 1940</date>, je n’ai jamais été<lb/> employé en tant que sanitaire : par
               conséquent,<lb/> ce paragraphe me concerne particulièrement.<lb/> C’est d’ailleurs,
               en vertu de cet accord, que<lb/> des infirmiers de mon groupe sanitaire
               divi-<lb/>sionnaire ont été libérés dans le courant du<lb/> mois de février.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Je vous serais donc très reconnaissant<lb/> de bien vouloir prendre en
                  considération ma si-<lb/>tuation présente.</salute>
               <signed corresp="#personJJ" rend="right">jJouzel</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prose" style="printed">
            <pb facs="#DSCF8350"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Au MARECHAL PETAIN <lb/> Chef de I’Etat Français</salute>
            </opener>
            <p rend="allcaps">LES PRISONNIERS DE GUERRE DU M.-STAMM-<lb/> LAGER XIII A ADRESSENT AU
               MARECHAL PE-<lb/> TAIN LEURS VOEUX TRES RESPECTUEUX A<lb/> L'OCCASION DE SON
               ANNIVERSAIRE. </p>
            <p rend="allcaps">ILS LUI EXPRIMENT LEUR RECONNAISSANCE<lb/> EMUE POUR LA GENEREUSE
               ATTENTION QU’IL<lb/> LEUR TEMOIGNE EN TOUTE CIRCONSTANCE<lb/> ET POUR TOUS SES
               EFFORTS EN VUE D’ADOU-<lb/> CIR, MORALEMENT ET MATERIELLEMENT, LEUR<lb/> CAPTIVITE. </p>
            <p>GARDANT UNE CONFIANCE INEBRANLABLE<lb/> DANS LES DESTINEES DE LA FRANCE ETER-<lb/>
               NELLE, ILS L’ASSURENT DE LEUR FILIAL AT-<lb/> TACHEMENT. </p>
            <closer>
               <signed rend="bold"><w>M.-STAMMLAGER XIIIA</w>M.-STAMMLAGER
                     XIIIA<lb/><w>Arbeits-Kommando</w>
                  <abbr>No. .............</abbr></signed>
               <signed><table cols="4" rows="20">
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>SIGNATURES</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>PRENOMS</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>PROFESSIONS</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>VILLES</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table></signed>
            </closer>




         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
